[Music]
Hello everyone and welcome back
to English Pod. My name is Marco.
My name is Katherine and today we
have an elementary level lesson for you.
That's right we are
going to talk about winter
but specifically about
the clothes you wear
during winter when it's
very, very cold outside.
That's right and I hear you're not too
familiar with some of these practices because
where you come from
you don't really have winter.
We don't have winter. We have dry season
and rainy season but same temperature.
Well Chicago definitely
has a snowy season so
I'm very familiar with these things so
let's jump right into today's dialogue.
We'll be hearing it one time and in a
minute we'll be back to talk about it.
[Music]
Bye mom.
Wait Jimmy, it's cold outside.
Put a hat on.
Okay bye.
No wait you'll be too cold without mittens.
All right see ya.
Hold on with that wind you're
going to catch a cold. Wear this scarf.
Okay see you after school and
earmuffs put these on. Here we go.
Oh yes honey. I can't breathe.
All right we're back so there were a couple
of different items of clothing that we saw
in this dialogue so let's look at
them now in language takeaway.
Language takeaway.
Okay well first of all we
have mom and Jimmy.
Jimmy is a boy's name.
He's a little boy and mom is
saying goodbye to him
but first she wants him
to put on clothes so the first item the
first thing she asks him to put on is a hat.
A hat. Now you've probably seen like a
baseball cap or many different types of hats
but and sometimes in
other languages they have
specific names for a hat for
winter right but in English it's a hat.
Anything that covers your head is a hat.
That's kind of like the category.
So maybe this one is a warm
wool hat but it's in the end it's a hat.
It's a hat. Okay so he's put on the hat
now what else is he going to put on?
Well we need to keep our
fingers warm okay so there
are two kinds of ways
to keep your fingers warm
and the way in this dialogue that the
boy keeps his fingers warm is with mittens.
All right so mittens
you put on your hands.
Now what's the difference
between mittens and gloves?
Okay gloves have special
places for each finger
1, 2, 3, 4, 5 on each
hand and mittens there's
two spaces one for your
thumb and one for all
your other fingers. Okay
so that means you can't
really hold things. So
you kind of look like a
penguin or something
like that. Yeah you look like
a yeah exactly like a
penguin and it's mostly
for children adults don't
wear mittens because
adults need to hold
things like keys and phones
and car, car steering
wheels. So in this case
mittens is usually for
children. Okay so mittens
and while the mother
is still a little bit worried
so she tells him
to wear a scarf.
Okay a scarf is all long usually
made of wool a long piece of
fabric that you put around your
neck to keep your neck warm.
Okay so a scarf. A scarf.
Okay and he's put on the
mittens the scarf the hat and he's
missing some ear muffs.
Okay this is the little
funny because usually
if you're wearing a hat
you don't need ear
muffs but ear muffs are like
headphones but they
keep your ears warm. Right.
And we wear these they
don't cover your head they
just cover your ears
and usually they're just
two round circles over
your ears. So as you say
exactly they look like big earphones
and they keep your ears warm.
Now as you say you usually don't wear this
if you're wearing a hat because well you
would put your ears
inside your hat right.
So it looks pretty silly if he's
wearing all of this together.
All right and so
those four key items
those four key pieces of
clothing are for our language
takeaway today when
we listen to this dialogue
again and we'll come back
soon to talk about fluency builder.
Bye mom. Wait Jimmy
it's cold outside but a hat
on. Okay bye no wait you'll
be too cold without mittens.
All right see ya.
Hold on with that
wind you're gonna catch
a cold. Where this scarf?
Okay see you after school.
Oh and ear muffs put these on. Here we go.
Yes honey. All right we're
back so now let's take
a look at four key
phrases on fluency builder.
Fluency builder. Okay
this first phrase as I said
before has to do with the
mom and the boy saying
goodbye to each other.
So he says all right see ya.
See ya. Yeah. Okay so
see as in to look to right
you see something and
what about YA? See ya.
So this is a very spoken
language way of saying you.
So we could say see
you later but if you want
to make it shorter you
can say see ya. See ya.
Bye. Bye goodbye. All right so see ya and
then what's our next way of saying goodbye.
Hold on. Oh wait that's
or not there yet no.
Hold on is our next phrase
and this is a way to say wait.
Wait hold on. So
you just say hold on it
means wait it's not
really rude right it's just a
little bit more casual.
Exactly it's very casual
so you cannot say hold
that doesn't make sense.
You have to use these two
words together. Hold on.
So like I said before with
Marco who wants to go
fast I get to say hold on.
Hold on. Wait a second.
All right okay so hold on
see ya and now you gotta
be careful because you're going
to catch a cold to catch a cold.
Okay so a cold is
when you you know
when you cough you have
a sore throat it's starting
to get cold outside
and you don't feel well.
Okay so you have a
running nose it's it's a illness
and most people get
this every year it's very
common but you don't get
a cold you catch a cold okay.
Okay so catch is the
same where we use for
when we we talk about sports
like throwing and catching.
Okay it's almost
like it just hits you it's
so fast you just catch
a cold. So that's really
important what you just
said because you don't use
the verb get you
don't get a cold.
You catch a cold or if you
say that you were sick last week
because you had a cold
you would say oh I caught
a cold or I had a cold.
Exactly so remember
present tense I catch a cold.
Passance I caught a cold last week.
Okay and our last phrase for fluency
builder is here we go. Here we go.
Okay so when do we hear this phrase
the mother says to the boy put these on.
Here we go so she's doing something
with him she's helping him put his ear
most on and here we
go is a way to say okay
I've finished okay I'm done
okay your earmuffs are on you.
So you're ready here you go.
Here you go. Right so we
say here we go like everything
is ready your earmuffs
are on. Exactly so maybe
I'm a computer and I have
a problem and I'm waiting
waiting waiting waiting
waiting and you know when
the bar's loading and
finally thing it's ready
here we go. Here we go
it's ready. Now it's ready
or sometimes a waitress
will come and serve you
food and say here we
go here's your order.
Exactly so this is a way to
say what you've been waiting
for it's ready now. Okay
great so I think it's time
for us to listen to this
dialogue one last time
before we come back.
Here we go. Bye mom.
Wait Jimmy it's cold outside
put a hat on. Okay bye no wait
you'll be too cold without mittens. All
right see ya. Hold on with that wind you're
gonna catch a cold
where this scarf.
Okay see ya after school and
earmuffs put these on here we go.
Mom yes honey. I can't
breathe. All right we're
back so as you mentioned
in Chicago it's very
very cold so I imagine
you had all of these
winter clothes right.
That's right and it's funny
because I remember
being a small child and my
mother doing this to
me putting on snow pants
and boots and earmuffs
and hats and gloves and
scarves and all the
sudden it's so hot inside
because you're wearing
everything and so you
can't even walk like you're
saying a pink you look
like a penguin walking
out the door and you get to
school and you're sweating
right and so in school
we had to take we had
a special room and we
had to take everything
off because there's snow
everywhere and snow can be very dangerous
because it melts and it turns into water.
Okay so I have very strong
memories of all of this putting
them on taking them off
and is being warm all the time.
Well yeah when it's
cold or you live in
a place with cold weather
you have to have these
items of clothing because
otherwise you might catch a cold.
Exactly so I hope that no one out
there catches a cold but if you want some
suggestions where a scarf
cover your neck that's the
most important you're head in
your scarf but that's important.
All right and if
you guys have any
other questions or comments
you can visit our website englishpot.
com and we'll see everyone
there. Bye everyone.